Hello everyone, and welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine, and today we have a
very weather focused lesson, it's all about
all the horrible things that can
happen to you with the weather.
Exactly, so as you know,
there are many different
types of weather, not
only rain or sunshine,
but many other phenomena, so we're going to
take a look at some of those, but before we
go into it, let's take a look at
one word on vocabulary preview.
Very Cablery Preview.
Okay, so we're talking
about extreme weather
today, that's not rain
or drizzle or sunshine.
We're talking about
really interesting, unique,
and sometimes
devastating things that can
happen, so today's vocabulary
word is Armageddon.
All right, so Armageddon,
now you've probably
seen the movie
Armageddon, so what does this
word mean? Okay, so this word is
a reference to the end of the world.
It means the time when
the world will end because
of a great catastrophe
or a great disaster.
Okay, so everyone talks about Armageddon.
It's mentioned in the Bible, and as you
say, it's when the world stops existing.
Exactly, so think about
that one as we listen
to today's dialogue,
we will be back in a
minute to talk about what's going on.
Those are the headlines
for today, and now
for the International Weather
Report with Mike Sanderson.
Thank you, Bob.
This past week has been the
beginning of Armageddon for many.
Has a series of unprecedented meteorological
events occurred around the world.
In Switzerland, a major
avalanche was reported
in the Alps, fortunately,
no one was injured.
Due to the extreme coldest winter, a
blizzard has struck the U.S. Midwest, causing
classes in schools and universities
to be temporarily canceled.
Moving on to Latin
America, Ecuador has
suffered a six-month
drought that has not only
affected farming, but
has also forced the closure
of the hydroelectric power plant that
provides electricity for the entire country.
In Chile, a major
earthquake that registered
7.5 on the Richter
scale struck the southern
region, losses are reported
to be in the billions.
Authorities have not yet
released an official statement.
Not a great week for the world.
Any good news?
I'm afraid not, Bob.
One of the major
volcanoes in Mexico has
erupted, causing major floods
and landslides in the region.
Meanwhile, Mexico's
coast has been hit by
Hurricane Iliana, and
officials say that all
the seismic activity
leads them to believe that
a tsunami made hit Central America,
affecting Honduras, Guatemala, and Panama.
That's all the news
we have for today, but
stay tuned for updates
on the six o'clock news.
Back to you, Bob.
All right, we're back,
and while this weather
report is not really
far from the truth,
I mean, this kind of stuff happens
every day all over the world, right?
That's correct.
And unfortunately, it's been happening very
frequently in the past couple of months.
We've heard of a lot of earthquakes
and volcanoes and things like that.
So this is very valuable
stuff when you're
trying to talk about
current events as well.
Okay.
So why don't we start
now analyzing a couple
of different words and
phrases on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Well the first vocabulary item we
have here is meteorological event.
It's a real mouthful to belong
where media are logical.
So for example,
meteorological means having to
do with the weather, something
that's related to the weather.
So a meteorological event
could be rain, snow, okay.
So it has to do with meteorology.
Meteorology is the
study of the weather, and
someone who does
this is a meteorologist.
So usually the weathermen that
you see on TV, they're meteorologist.
So let's go now to
Marco, our resident
meteorologist, our
resident meteorologist, okay.
So meteorological events.
Now moving on, one of the first events that
we're going to look at is an avalanche.
An avalanche has to
do with snow, this means
that when a mountain
that has a lot of snow
on it, maybe it's part
of that so breaks off
and starts to roll down, you have
a wall of snow that comes down.
That's an avalanche.
So you could say "Avella"
and the snow comes down.
And it's actually very dangerous because
people can get buried under the snow.
Yeah, exactly.
All right, so another event that
has to do with snow is a blizzard.
Okay, a blizzard is
different from an avalanche
because an avalanche,
maybe it's not snowing.
The snow just falls.
But in a blizzard, you're
talking about a storm
of snow, but it's like a lot of
snow coming down from the sky.
So much snow that you probably can't see
anything, there's just white everywhere.
Okay.
All right, so that's a blizzard, a lot
of snow coming down from the sky.
Now moving on, the opposite of snow
and things being wet is we have a drought.
Yeah, this is the opposite of wet,
actually, so there's no rain in a drought.
A drought means that things are very dry.
The land is very dry.
Okay, so it's a period of
time that there's no snow,
there's no water, there's
no rain, there's nothing.
It's very, very dry.
We're going through a drought.
Correct, and the
problem with a drought is
very dangerous is because
people cannot grow
food in a drought, and so lots of
people starve when this happens.
Okay, so I've got to
watch out for a drought.
Now, in this case,
it not only affected
farming, but also we
have a hydroelectric power
plant that can't work, obviously,
because there's no water.
So hydro means water.
Hydroelectric means electricity
that is generated by flowing water.
And so, for example,
a mill, something that
turns water on our river is a
way to get power from water.
But a hydroelectric
project that can give you
electricity is maybe like
a dam or an electric mill.
Right, so usually you have these in rivers
and they just take advantage of the flowing
of water to turn some huge
turbines and generate power.
So that's all we have for now.
Why don't we listen to the dialogue again?
And we'll be back shortly to
take a look at some more words.
Those are the headlines
for today, and now
for the International Weather
Report with Mike Sanderson.
Thank you, Bob.
This past week has
been the beginning of
Armageddon for many, as
a series of unprecedented
meteorological events
occurred around the world.
In Switzerland, a major
avalanche was reported
in the Alps, fortunately
no one was injured.
Due to the extreme
coldest winter, a blizzard
has struck the U.S.
Midwest, causing classes
in schools and universities
to be temporarily canceled.
Moving on to Latin
America, Ecuador has suffered
a six-month drought
that has not only affected
farming, but has also
forced the closure of the
hydroelectric power plant that provides
electricity for the entire country.
In Chile, a major
earthquake that registered
7.5 on the Richter scale
struck the southern region.
Houses are reported
to be in the billions,
authorities have not yet
released an official statement.
Not a great week for the world.
Any good news?
I'm afraid not, Bob.
One of the major volcanoes
in Mexico has erupted,
causing major floods and
landslides in the region.
Meanwhile, Mexico's
coast has been hit by
Hurricane Liliana,
and officials say that all
the seismic activity
leads them to believe that
a tsunami made hit Central America,
affecting Honduras, Guatemala, and Panama.
That's all the news
we have for today, but
stay tuned for updates
on the six o'clock news.
Back to you, Bob.
Well, a word that many
people are unfortunately
familiar with is
Richter or Richter scale.
And now this is
something that a lot of
people are talking about
right now because of
the earthquake in Sichuan China last year,
and the earthquake in Haiti very recently.
And so the Richter
scale, that's a big R,
because it's a proper
name, is a way for us to
determine how severe,
how big the earthquake was.
Right, so people talk about a 6.0,
a 7.1, so that's on the Richter scale.
The lowest is zero and
the highest is 10, correct?
Right, but 10 is like
impossible, apparently.
Apparently, and a lot
of them are actually
underwater, but the very
serious ones are maybe 8.0, 7.0.
All right, so Richter scale.
Now we talked about
earthquakes, we talked
about snowing, now
let's talk about a volcano.
A volcano in Mexico has erupted.
Okay, so we've got two words here, volcano.
A volcano is a mountain that has an opening
in the center where lava from the middle of
the earth, the center of
the earth can come out.
So it's very dangerous,
obviously, because it's very hot.
Right.
But a volcano doesn't open, it erupts.
So the verb here that we use
without volcano is too erupt.
Okay, so it doesn't
explode, a volcano erupts.
That means to open violently very quickly.
Okay, so when this happens, obviously,
you have a lot of lava, you have maybe snow
that melts, and you have
floods and landslides.
Okay, land slides, a
landslide is one word,
but it's made up of two words
that you probably already know.
So land, obviously, it's the ground,
the things like that, the earth.
But a slide is to move
down across the ground.
And so a landslide
happens when you've got
something like lava or water that's pushing
all of the earth, all of the ground down.
And it's destroying houses and trees
and land, and it's very, very destructive.
Right, so you usually see this that happens
on the side of mountains, on the side of
hills where all that land starts
to slide down or to go down.
And it's very similar
to an avalanche, right?
But instead of snow falling
down, it's a mud and land, yeah.
All right, so we have a landslide.
And because of all the
eruptions and the earthquakes,
they said that they have
a lot of seismic activity.
This word seismic is something that I've
heard a lot recently in movies, like 2012.
So seismic means
having to do with the
movements of the plates
under the earth's crust.
So, you know, the earth
is not everything that
we see, it's also activity, things
happening underneath the ground.
And so underneath the
ground, we have these big plates.
And seismic activity is what happens
when these kind of things start to move.
Activity is movement.
And so seismic activity
refers to earthquakes
and volcanoes, things that are changing
under the ground that will affect us.
Okay.
So that seismic activity is
pronounced seismic, right?
Seismek.
That's correct.
Okay.
And because of all this activity,
people say that they may have a tsunami.
Well, this doesn't sound
very English, doesn't.
I know, tsunami.
And actually, if you see
this spelling, it's with a TTS.
Right.
I think it's a Japanese
word, but I'm not positive.
I think so too.
Tsunami is the name that
we give to a giant tidal wave.
So that's a wave of
water in the ocean that's
very, very dangerous because
it can get 200, 200 feet tall.
And this means that
when it comes down, it
can destroy houses,
cities, cars, things like that.
Right.
And there was a very,
very famous tsunami in
Southeast Asia in 2004,
do you remember that?
Yeah.
And in Indonesia, right?
That's right.
Indonesia and Thailand.
Yeah.
It was intense.
It was big.
And it was also because
of the earthquake, right?
I think so.
These earthquakes,
they move the earth
around, and then all
of a sudden, the reaction
is that there's water that moves in
the water, then it turns into a wave.
Yeah.
Just imagine what happens with you.
If you have a bucket
of water and then you
start moving the
bucket just a little bit and
just you see how it just water
starts to splat all over the place.
That's right.
All right.
So tsunami was our last
word for today when we listen
to our dialogue again
and we'll be back shortly.
[MUSIC]
Those are the headlines
for today and now for
the International Weather
Report with Mike Sanderson.
Thank you, Bob.
This past week has been the
beginning of Armageddon for many.
Has a series of unprecedented meteorological
events occurred around the world.
In Switzerland, a major
avalanche was reported
in the Alps, fortunately,
no one was injured.
Due to the extreme coldest winter, a
blizzard has struck the U.S. Midwest, causing
classes in schools and universities
to be temporarily canceled.
Moving on to Latin
America, Ecuador has suffered
a six-month drought
that has not only affected
farming, but has also
forced the closure of the
hydroelectric power plant that provides
electricity for the entire country.
In Chile, a major
earthquake that registered
7.5 on the Richter
scale struck the southern
region, losses are reported
to be in the billions.
Anyways, have not yet
released an official statement.
Not a great week for the world.
Any good news?
I'm afraid not, Bob.
One of the major
volcanoes in Mexico has
erupted, causing major floods
and landslides in the region.
Meanwhile, Mexico's
coast has been hit by
Hurricane Liliana and
officials say that all
the seismic activity
leads them to believe that
a tsunami made hit Central America,
affecting Honduras, Guatemala, and Panama.
That's all the news we have for today, but
stay tuned for updates on the six o'clock
news back to You, Bob.
So Marco, these are all pretty terrifying.
Have you ever experienced
a meteorological event
like one of the ones that
we talked about today?
I've actually lived it through like
three earthquakes, like pretty big ones.
Plus, because you used
to live in Los Angeles, too.
So you get them all the time in LA.
Apart from that, I
actually, I've seen a
volcano erupt a couple
of times because, you
know, Ecuador is a, it's part
of the volcano alley, right?
It's all the Andes Mountains and it's
part of the circle of fire, what they call.
So we have a couple
of different active
volcanoes and from time
and time, they will start
to smoke or to spew
some lava, but nothing
major, like there hasn't
been a major catastrophe
with the volcanoes,
hopefully it won't either.
Well, in these days,
they have a lot of
equipment, seismic
equipment and meteorological
equipment that can
help meteorologists to
determine when things
will happen, like when
a volcano will erupt
or if there will be an
earthquake because they can
study the tremors in the ground.
Right.
Yeah.
And I think probably the most famous
volcano is, I think it was in Italy, right?
Mount Vesuvius.
That's right, so you've
got Mount Vesuvius
in Naples, which famously
destroyed a number
of cities in this ancient civilization
in ancient-- But it's a major eruption.
It was.
And what's amazing
is that they still have a
lot of the buildings
under the ash, because
when all the ash settled, it preserved the
bodies like a mummy, and so you can see the
bodies and the things that they, you know,
they're jewelry and they're money and it's
fascinating because
it's this horrible,
horrible natural disaster
actually helped us in
the future learn about
this old civilization.
And it's crazy actually
in Ecuador, you can see
a huge hole that has
like a lake in the middle.
And you know, like,
oh wow, that's beautiful,
but that's actually
caused because the entire
mountain just kind
of blew the top off, like
the cone because of
this major eruption.
So you can just imagine how
powerful these eruptions are.
You can just imagine what it would
have been like Mount Vesuvius.
But anyway, on a brighter note, if you have
any questions, any comments or any stories
of your own, maybe
you've lived through a
typhoon or hurricane or tornado, you can
come to our website, www.EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
All right.
Bye guys.